RAJINDER KUMAR

Mobile: 09569730215

8728830571

E-mail: rajintbilisi@gmail.com

razsaini@rediff.com

Synopsis:

B.E. Chemical, MBA, PG Diploma in Industrial Safety with **15 years** of experience in Plant Operations, Safety, Maintenance, Cost Reduction, Supply chain Management, Project Management, Cost Reduction, Production Planning & Control, Quality Control/Assurance, Lean manufacturing, Kaizen,5 S, ISO, SAP implementation, ERP, out sourcing, Vendor Management and Man Management.

Objective:

To share my experience with your esteemed organization & seeking a Responsible & Challenging position in a Dynamic organization.

Professional Qualifications:

- B.E. Chemical with 1st division in July 2000 From Sant Longowal Instt. Of Eng. & Tech.(established by Govt. of India) affiliated with Punjab Tech. University Jallandhar (pb.) India
- MBA executive from Punjab University Chandigarh (India) in year 2007.
- Post Diploma in Industrial Safety from R.L.I Faridabad (India) in 2010.
- Certified Lead Auditor for ISO 9001:2008 from BUREAO VERITAS

Professional experience:

Company: GEORGIA RUBBER LLC

Address: Tbilisi, Georgia Designation: **Plant Manager**

Duration: From Nov 2012 to 15 Mar 2016.

Company Profile: Manufacturing rubber products from waste tyres.

Job Profile:

To plan, direct and coordinate operations Responsible for ensuring and improving the performance, productivity, efficiency, safety and profitability of departmental and organizational operations.

Production

- To maximize productivity by: Eliminating the bottlenecks in process.
- Effective org. and utilization of Men, Materials, Machine and Methods.
- To identify, plan and implement cost reduction measures, without compromising on production efficiency.

Safety

- To introduce and establish global best practices.
- To put in place systems to identify & remove unsafe cond. and activities.
- To comply with all safety related statutory requirements.
- To frame the related safety documentations and policies.

- To ensure and improve the safety standards of work practices for equipment and personnel safety.
- To comply with all environmental norms specified by the Pollution Control Board. Include the same in ETP to proposed production plans.
- To identify and implement water conservation measures.
- To bring about improvements in the process, with the prior approval of management. Responsible for increasing the safety levels in process.

Projects

- To take lead in all projects and modernization initiatives.
- To manage, monitor and guide the project team.
- To identify value creating, cost reducing and debottlenecking projects.
- To track all projects and ensure tech and commercial goals are achieved.

Energy

- To bring about continuous improvement in the energy consumption of routine activities.
- To identify, plan and implement potential energy saving projects.

Quality

- To ensure that products match the specifications given in the data sheet.
- To completely reduce the number of customer complaints. Achieve customer satisfaction by keeping production costs stable.

Maintenance and Utility

- To ensure maintenance schedules are made for all the equipment and the same is monitored effectively.
- To improve and increase the vendor base for better products, equipment, spares and projects.
- To improve the engineering spares inventory.

Company: Afton Chemical Hyderabad Pvt Ltd (A part of Afton Chemical Ltd, U.S.A)

Address: Hyderabad (AP.)
Designation: **Plant Manager**

Duration: From 2 Feb 2011 to 30 oct 2012

Company Profile: ISO 9001-2000 Company for Design and Manufacturing of innovative Chemical Products related to metal working, metal treatment, making of Esters. Amides and anti-corrosive chemicals.

Job Profile:

- Responsible for production, maintenance, EHS, Logistics, Statutory compliance, HR & Admin, projects and supply chain.
- Plant Operations, Project Management, Vendor Management, Production, Cost Reduction, Logistic, Man Management, Safety, Capacity enhancement.
- Liasoning with various govt departments/authorities for obtaining permissions, approvals clearences for seamless plant operations.
- Training & development of employees, developing second line of leadership,
- Setting up & managing entire plant operations with a view to ahieve business objective and profitability.

- Controlling factory expenses with in the approved budget and plan savings in overheads, utility cost with optimising resources.
- Supply chain management: Scope Storage and handling of raw material.
- For optimizing the products costs through continual process optimization
- For Plant Management .(Ensuring effective utilization of plant capacities)
- For Plant Operations. (Ensuring safety as well as compliance of SOPs)
- For Monitoring of Plant Performance. (Optimization of resources)
- For Plant Inspection and Condition Monitoring. (Ensuring the healthiness of various equipments)
- For Material Management. (Coordinating and ensuring the procurement of RM/PM in time to avoid any possibility of neither production loss due to shortage of material nor excess inventory level build up)
- Achieving Targeted Production, Yield as well as Quality.
- Ensuring compliance of ISO 9001, ISO 14001 and 18001.
- For Safety Management in the Plant. (Through time to time arranging training programmes).

Company: High Polymer Labs Additives Ltd (ISO-9001, ISO-14000 and

OHSAS- 18000 certified company)

Address: Faridabad (HR.) India

Designation: **Dy Manager Production**Duration: From 12 May 2008 to 28 jan 2011

Company Profile: High Polymer Labs is second largest manufacturer of a wide range of polymer additives in India consisting of multi locational companies. HPLA born in 1964 is now engaged in the manufacturing of Antioxidants, UV stabilizers, blowing agents and many other polymer additives.

Field of exposure:

- 1. Production of Speciality Chemicals (Polymer Additive), Antioxidants, UV Stabilizer which involve various operations like Batch wise Reactor, Distillation Crystallizer, and Filtration & Rotary Dryer with DCS control system.
- 2. Solvent Recovery Plant Methanol, ACN, MDC, Toluene, Xylene, IPA etc

Working exposure on

Distillation units (atmospheric and vacuum), Solvent Recovery, heat exchangers, condensers, blowers, Rotary vacuum filters, dryers, plate and frame filter presses, centrifugal & positive displacement pumps, Candle filters, CSTR reactor, MSGL Reactors cyclone separator, Pulverizers, ventury scrubbers, packed bed scrubbers, Crystallizer, ANFD, Steam and water ring vacuum systems PLC and DCS based controlling of above mentioned units .

Job Responsibilities

- 1 Focusing on areas like cost reduction / improvement of productivity.
- 2 Responsible for supervision, Training and Development of all plant production operators.
- 3 Technical training of all workers to operate work on Quality, Safety, SHE and 5 S.

- 4 A member of HAZOP analysis team.
- 5 Production, Process control, Planning & Management, Safe & Smooth Operation of Plant operations.
- 6 Responsible for all preventive maintenance activities.
- 7 Ensure maximum coordination with different departments.
- 8 Ensure quality of all the products and intermediates are as per the defined standards.
- 9 Ensure that employees are adequately trained in Safety and GMP related areas.
- 10 To counsel employees in consultation with HR in case of any serious issue.
- 11 Work on shop floor to maintain EHS standard working with the team.
- 12 Coordinate EHS activities.
- 13 Identify unsafe action and unsafe condition. Maintain, update, monitor and ensure compliance EHS procedure & practices. Contractor labor safety management.
- 14 Development and implementation of Safety Procedures.
- 15 Conduction Mock drills.
- 16 Safety audits and inspection.

Past experience

Company: ANSYSCO

Address: No: 19-F, Sector- 2, Industrial Area, Parwanoo, Himachal Pradesh.

Duration: From 10 Jan 2004 to 16 Apr 2008.

Designation: Sr. Engineer

Company Profile: A member of ANAND GROUP(Anand Automotive component) having an annual turnover of 2200 crores, is a leading manufacturer of a wide range of automotive components in INDIA consisting of multi locational companies. Ansysco born in 1995 is now engaged in the manufacturing of Radiator coolants, PVC Adhesives, Waxes, wind shield washer and many other Car Care Products.

Job Responsibilities:

- 1 Responsible for the process monitoring of PVC Adhesive, Radiator Coolant, Wax polishes and Wind shield washer.
- 2 Leading a team of 45 workers for effective production of coolants, PVC Adhesives and waxes.
- 3 Responsible for a minimum production of 500 tons of Radiator coolant, 75tons and 15 tons of waxes on a three-shift basis.
- 4 Production planning and control.
- 5 Responsible for manpower planning & control.
- 6 Responsible for In-process testing and sampling of final product.
- 7 Responsible for the dispatch and quality of finished goods
- **8** Responsible for production according to JIS standards, FIFO system and Indian standards.

Past experience

September15,2000 to 9 Jan 2004. **INDIAN ACRYLICS LIMITED (ISO-9001:2000)** Sangrur, Punjab as Shift engineer (Indian Acrylics Limited – A Steel Strips Group Company of present turnover of 750 crores in Technical Corporation with E.I.Du pont Nemours & Chemtex Engg. USA, it is a major producer of acrylic fiber in India)

- 1 Attended 2 days training on First Aid from Red Cross (St. **John Ambulance**).
- 2 Attended 3 days training on Supervisory Training for Actions & Results.
- 3 Attended 2 days training on Behavioral Leadership.
- 4 Got 1st prize in best implementation of **5 S** in ANSYSCO.

Strengths

- 1 Superior ability to achieve immediate and long-term goal.
- 2 Capable to supervise and manage Operating activities under critical and emergency situations.
- 3 Capable to overcome on any type of job very easily.
- 4 Ability to execute a number of projects simultaneously.
- 5 Self-motivated and strong interpersonal skills.
- 6 Excellent written and oral communication ability.
- 7 Hardworking and leadership skill.

Computer Literacy

Basic fundamental, WINDOWS, MS Office, ERP, SAP

Interest / Hobbies

Yoga, Meditation, Traveling, Music, Internet, Driving and Housekeeping.

Personal Details

• DOB - 21-04-1976

• Willing to relocate - Yes

• Expected CTC - Negotiable

(Rajinder Kumar)